There are common ways to notate most aggregations.
توجد طرق شائعة لتدوين تجميعات كثيرة.
An aggregation is just a way to turn multiple numbers into fewer numbers,
التجميعة هي طريقة لتحويل أرقام عديدة إلى أرقام أقل،
usually just one number.
عادةً إلى رقم واحد.
Common aggregations include the measures of center we introduced earlier,
تتضمن التجميعات الشائعة قياسات المركز التي قدمناها سابقًا،
like the mean, the median, and the mode.
مثل المعنى والوسيط والوضع.
Each of these takes many numbers and provides
يأخذ كل من هذه العديد من الارقام ويقدم
a single value to give information about the data set.
قيمة واحدة لتعطي معلومات عن مجموعة البيانات.
In this example, we want to aggregate all the values into a single sum.
في هذا المثال، نريد تجميع كل القيم في مجموع واحد.
In other words, add them up.
بمعنى آخر، نريد أن نجمعهم.
The Greek alphabet is a popular place to pull notation.
الأبجدية اليونانية هي مكان شائع لسحب للتدوين.
Similar to English, there are both lower and upper case letters in the Greek alphabet.
تمامًا مثل الإنجليزية، يوجد بالأبجدية اليونانية حروف صغيرة وحروف كبيرة.
For summing many values together,
لجمع عدة قيم معًا،
we use a Greek symbol known as Sigma.
نستخدم رمز يوناني معروف باسم سيجما.
Specifically, we use the uppercase Sigma.
تحديدًا نستخدم الحرف الكبير سيجما.
We generally use the symbol in the following way:
بشكل عام نستخدم الرمز بالطرق التالية:
you will notice that instead of writing multiple x values,
ستلاحظ أنه بدلاً من كتابة القيمة x مرات عديدة،
each with a different subscript,
كل واحد برمز سفلي مختلف،
we write a single x with a subscript of i.
نكتب x مرة واحدة بنص سفلي i.
Here, the I is a placeholder that tells us which x values we'll be summing up.
هنا، i هي عنصر نائب يخبرنا أي من قيم x سيتم تجميعها.
In our first case,
في الحالة الأولى،
summing only the first two values,
جمع القيمتين الأولين فقط،
we want this i to be the value of either one or two.
نريد أن تكون i هذه قيمة لواحد أو اثنين.
Now you might be asking,
الآن، قد تتساءل،
how does this notation show which values we're summing together.
كيف يُظهر هذا التدوين أي القيم نجمعها معًا.
This is a great question.
إنه سؤال رائع.
If we would like to sum just the first two values,
إذا أردنا تجميع القيمتين الأولتين فقط،
we would write something like this.
سنكتب شيء ما كهذا.
Notice at the bottom,
لاحظ في الاسفل،
we are giving our starting point.
نكتب نقطة بدايتنا.
That is, we would like the first x value to be where i equals one.
ها هي، نريد أن تكون قيمة x الأولى حيث تساوي واحد.
You can imagine replacing the one into this subscript.
يمكنك تخيل استبدال واحد في هذا النص السفلي.
Then the value at the top gives us an ending point for where we stop.
ثم القيمة العلوية تعطينا نقطة النهاية حيث نتوقف.
Here, our ending is two.
هنا، نهايتنا هي اثنين.
The Sigma tells us we would like to sum from
تخبرنا سيجما أننا نريد الجمع من
this bottom value up through all the values until we hit this top value.
هذه القيمة السفلية مرورًا بكل القيم لأعلى حتى نصل لهذه القيمة العلوية.
The new notation, with the summation symbol,
التدوين الجديد، برمز الجمع،
is the same as our original notation of x1 + x2.
هو نفس التدوين الأصلي للقيم x1 + x2.